# MATTEO PEZZULLA

@ matt@mpe.au.dkmpezzulla.comSkype ID: matteo.pezzulla

ÅRHUS, DK

Date of Birth: August 3, 1988

CITIZENSHIP: Italian

### Summary of qualifications & assets

I am an Assistant Professor in the Department of Mechanical Engineering at Aarhus University.

My current research involves aspects of fluid-structure interactions and the theoretical and applied mechanics of thin shells. I work among solid mechanics, fluid mechanics, and differential geometry and I am interested in analytical, numerical, and experimental methods.

I am a member of the American Physical Society (APS).

#### Experience

Nov 2020 – currently Tenure Track Assistant Professor at Aarhus University

Nov 2017 – Oct 2020 Postdoctoral Associate at École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne Supervisor: Prof. Pedro M. Reis

Nov 2015 – Oct 2017 Postdoctoral Associate at Boston University Supervisor: Prof. Douglas P. Holmes

#### EDUCATION

FEBRUARY 2016 Ph.D. in THEORETICAL AND APPLIED MECHANICS,

Sapienza - Università di Roma

with honors

Focus: Morphing of Thin Soft Structures Driven by Geometry and Swelling

Advisor: Prof. Paola NARDINOCCHI

Aug – Dec 2014 Visiting Scholar at Boston University

Advisor: Prof. Douglas P. Holmes

October 2012 M.Sc. in Space Engineering, Sapienza - Università di Roma

110/110 cum laude

Thesis: "On the control of the large deformations occurring in IPMCs"

Advisor: Prof. Paola NARDINOCCHI

October 2010 B.Sc. in Aerospace Engineering, Sapienza - Università di Roma

110/110 cum laude

Thesis: "Bending deformations in ionic polymer metal composites induced by

mechano-electro-chemical interactions"

Advisor: Prof. Paola NARDINOCCHI

I

#### **INVITED SEMINARS**

- 2022 Morphing of slender structures via elastic instabilities. CITA, Copenhagen, Denmark, March.
- A Geometrically Exact Model for Thin Magneto-elastic Shells. Sapienza University of Rome, Rome, Italy, September.
- 2020 Towards Fluid-Shells Interactions. Aarhus University, Aarhus, Denmark, April.
- 2016 Geometry and Instabilities in Growing Shells. Sapienza Università di Roma, Rome, Italy, December.
- 2016 Geometry and Instabilities in Growing Shells. Physical Mathematics Seminar, MIT, Cambridge, MA, October
- Morphing of geometric composites. Form Finding Workshop, Roma Tre University, Rome, Italy, April.
- Morphing of Geometric Composites via Residual Swelling. Bertoldi Group Meeting, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, December.

## JOURNALS & CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

- H. Garg, P. G. Ledda, J. S. Pedersen, and M. Pezzulla. Passive viscous flow selection via fluid-induced buckling. *Submitted*. Available at arXiv:2402.11966.
- K. Barvenik, Z. Coogan, G. Librandi, M. Pezzulla, and E. Tubaldi. Tactile Sensing and Grasping Through Thin-Shell Buckling. Adv. Intell. Syst. 2300855 (2024).
- Y. L. Lin, M. Pezzulla, and P. M. Reis. Fluid-structure interactions of bristled wings: The trade-off between weight and drag. J. R. Soc. Interface 20, 20230266 (2023).
- P. G. Ledda, M. Pezzulla, E. Jambon-Puillet, P.-T. Brun, and F. Gallaire. Gravity-driven coatings on curved substrates: a differential geometry approach. *J. Fluid Mech.* 949, A38 (2022).
- P. Leroy-Calatayud, M. Pezzulla, A. Keiser, K. Mulleners, and P. M. Reis. Tapered foils favor traveling-wave kinematics to enhance the performance of flapping propulsion. *Phys. Rev. Fluids* 7, 074403 (2022).
- M. Pezzulla, D. Yan, and P. M. Reis. A geometrically exact model for thin magneto-elastic shells. *J. Mech. Phys. Solids* 166, 104916 (2022).
- T. G. Sano, M. Pezzulla, and P. M. Reis. A Kirchhoff-like theory for hard magnetic rods under three-dimensional geometrically nonlinear deformation. *J. Mech. Phys. Solids* 160, 104739 (2022).
- B. Shrimali, M. Pezzulla, S. Poincloux, P. M. Reis, and O. Lopez-Pamies. The remarkable bending properties of perforated plates. *J. Mech. Phys. Solids* 154, 104514 (2021).
- D. Yan, M. Pezzulla, L. Cruveiller, A. Abbasi, and P. M. Reis. Magneto-active elastic shells with tunable buckling strength. *Nat. Commun.* 12, 2831 (2021).
- M. Pezzulla, E. F. Strong, F. Gallaire, and P. M. Reis. Deformation of porous flexible strip in low and moderate Reynolds number flows. *Phys. Rev. Fluids* 5, 084103 (2020)
- D. P. Holmes, J.-H. Lee, H. S. Park, and M. Pezzulla. The nonlinear buckling behavior of a complete spherical shell under uniform external pressure and homogenous natural curvature. *Phys. Rev. E* 102, 023003 (2020)
- D. Yan, M. Pezzulla, and P. M. Reis. Buckling of pressurized spherical shells containing a throughthickness defect. J. Mech. Phys. Solids 138, 103923 (2020)

- M. Pezzulla and P. M. Reis. A Weak Form Implementation of Nonlinear Axisymmetric Shell Equations with Examples. ASME. J. Appl. Mech. 86(12): 124502, (2019)
- E. F. Strong, M. Pezzulla, F. Gallaire, P. M. Reis, and L. Siconolfi. Hydrodynamic loading of perforated disks in creeping flows. *Phys. Rev. Fluids* 4, 084101, (2019)
- A. Lee, D. Yan, M. Pezzulla, D. P. Holmes, and P. M. Reis. Evolution of critical buckling conditions in imperfect bilayer shells through residual swelling. *Soft Matter* 15, 6134-6144, (2019)
- L. Stein-Montalvo, P. Costa, M. Pezzulla and D. P. Holmes. Buckling of Geometrically Confined Shells. *Soft Matter* 15, 1215-1222, (2019)
- X. Jiang, M. Pezzulla, S. Wei, T. K. Ghosh, and D. P. Holmes. Snapping of Bistable, Prestressed Cylindrical Shells. *Europhys. Lett.* 122, 64003, (2018)
- M. Pezzulla, N. Stoop, M. P. Steranka, A. J. Bade, and D. P. Holmes. Curvature-Induced Instabilities of Shells. *Phys. Rev. Lett.* 120, 048002, (2018)
- 2017 M. Pezzulla, N. Stoop, X. Jiang, and D. P. Holmes. Curvature-Driven Morphing of Non-Euclidean Shells. *Proc. R. Soc. A* 473(2201), 20170087, (2017)
- M. Pezzulla, G. P. Smith, P. Nardinocchi, and D. P. Holmes. Geometry and Mechanics of Thin Growing Bilayers. *Soft Matter* 12, 4435-4442, (2016)
- P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, and L. Teresi. Steady and transient analysis of anisotropic swelling in fibered gels. J. Appl. Phys. 118, 244904, (2015)
- M. Pezzulla, S. A. Shillig, P. Nardinocchi, and D. P. Holmes. Morphing of geometric composites via residual swelling. *Soft Matter* 11, 5812-5820, (2015) [Inside Front Cover]
- P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, and L. Teresi, Mechanics of bio-hybrid systems. *Procedia IUTAM* 12, pp. 145-153, (2015)
- P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, and L. Teresi, Anisotropic swelling of thin gel sheets. *Soft Matter* 11, 1492-1499, (2015)
- A. Lucantonio, P. Nardinocchi, and M. Pezzulla. Swelling-induced and controlled curving in layered gel beams. *Proc. R. Soc. A* 470(2171), 20140467, (2014)
- A. Lucantonio, P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, and L. Teresi. Multiphysics of bio-hybrid systems: shape control and electro-induced motion. *Smart Mater. Struct.* 23(4), 045043, (2014)
- P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, B.J. Akle, M. Guenther, and T. Wallmersperger. Actuation and buckling effects in IPMCs. *Proc. SPIE* 9056, (2014)
- Y. Cha, P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, and M. Porfiri. Giant displacements in IPMC-based structures: a preliminary study. Adv. Mat. Res. 745, 119–128, (2013)
- P.Nardinocchi and M. Pezzulla. Curled actuated shapes of ionic polymer metal composites. J. Appl. Phys. 113, 224906, (2013)
- P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, and L. Placidi. Thermodynamically based multiphysic modeling of ionic polymer metal composites. *J. Intel. Mat. Syst. Str.* 22(16), 1887–1897, (2011)

#### CURRENT GROUP MEMBERS

- 2024- Morten Opstrup Andersen, PhD Student (HFSP project)
- 2023- Hemanshul Garg, Postdoctoral Researcher (VILLUM Experiment project)

## Honors & Grants

| 2023      | HFSP, Research grant - Program, co-PI (USD 1.5M),   |  |
|-----------|---|--|
| 2023      | The Royal Society, International Exchanges, co-PI (GBP 5k),   |  |
| 2022      | VILLUM Experiment, VILLUM Fonden, PI (DKK 2M),  |  |
| 2022      | Thomas B. Thriges Fond, PI (DKK 40k),   |  |
| 2016      | PHASME 2016 Travel Grant, ICAM (USD 1k),  |  |
| 2014      | Research Project Grant <i>Giovani Ricercatori</i> , INdAM (€ 1.6k), "Corrugamento di travi bistrato di gel polimerico"                            |  |
| 2014      | Research Project Young Investigator Grant, Sapienza University ( € 2k), "Shaping of bio-hybrid systems: reduced models and numerical simulations" |  |
| 2013-2015 | Graduate Research Fellowship, Italian Ministry of Education   |  |
| 2007-2012 | ADISU scholarship   |  |

## TEACHING, TEACHING QUALIFICATIONS, AND SERVICE

| 2024  | Co-organizer of the $58^{\mathrm{th}}$ meeting of the Society for Natural Philosophy, Aarhus                     |  |
|-------|--|--|
| 2024  | $Co-organizer\ of\ the\ Symposium:\ Mechanics\ of\ Soft\ Materials\ and\ Structures,\ at\ EMMC19,\ Madrid$       |  |
| 2024  | Foundational course in PhD Supervision, Diploma  |  |
| 2021- | Courses: Slender Structures, Theory of Elasticity<br>AU, Instructor  |  |
| 202I  | University Pedagogical Programme at AU, Diploma  |  |
| 202I- | Member of the Education Committee at AU  |  |
| 2019  | Lectures on shells for the class on <i>Mechanics of Slender Structures</i> EPFL, Instructor: Prof. Pedro M. Reis |  |

## Language & Programming Skills

- \* Mother tongue: Italian. Fluent in English and French. B2 in Spanish and Danish.
- \* Experience programming in C, Fortran, and Python.
- ★ Experience with mathematical software such as Matlab, Mathematica, LabView, LabVi
- ★ Experience with FE software such as COMSOL Multiphysics, ADINA, Nastran.
- \* Experience with Adobe Illustrator, Blender, MeshLab, Paraview and ImageJ.

|  | C       | ?æ   |
|--|---------|------|
|  | June, 2 | .024 |